The next topic we're going to cover goes
a bit more in depth about managing various
aspects of the Java thread lifecycle.
So we're going to talk about what
the Java thread lifecycle is,
we're going to talk about how
to manage it effectively.
The main focus of this discussion really
deals with learning how to stop or
interrupt Java threads, gracefully.
We'll first start by talking about
the different states in the Java thread
lifecycle.
A thread, as you might imagine is actually
a very complicated entity that interacts
with lots other things, both at
the hardware level and the software level.
And so you have to know how these threads
works, the state of the threads and
you have to understand how to manage
their lifecycle very carefully.
So there's about seven
different states and
we're going to talk about each of them.
Two of the most important parts of Java
involve starting and stopping threads, so
we're going to pay
particular emphasis there.
To use Java threads effectively,
you don't have to understand all
the inner details we're about to discuss,
that's only for people who want to
have sort of wizard level knowledge.
But it doesn't hurt to have
a good understanding of these,
because you'll often run into situations
where your concurrent programs don't work
correctly and
knowing how the threads transition between
different states in there lifecycle can
help you with debugging various defects
that have crept into your code.
We'll start by talking about
the state machine for Java threads.
As you can see,
there's again seven main states.
You can see the states
here in the documentation.
There's also a nice UML diagram that gives
you another more visual view of these
states then what I've shown here.
When you create a thread,
when you say, new thread object,
new my thread or new thread, etc..
That transitions the state
machine to the new state,
which just allocates a few resources for
the thread object.
When you start the thread, that completes
the initialization by creating more
resource intensive
objects like a stack and
that then makes the thread
transition into the runnable state.
Now just because you say start,
doesn't mean the threads actually running.
All it means is that it's able to run and
it's the schedule that decides whether or
not to run the threads and
when to run them.
When a schedule selects a runnable
thread to run, it begins to run and
that is the run hook
method gets called back.
If during the running of the run hook
method, the thread sleeps, waits or
joins with operations that have
a time out associated with them,
that transitions to
the timed waiting state.
And the thread will then, basically,
be deactivated until the time period
elapses or
whatever else it's doing occurs.
Like if the wait If it's notified or is,
it's the other thread its going to join
with, it's going to be exited,
et cetera, then it'll transition out
of the timed waiting state and
it becomes runnable again.
But again, it doesn't start running,
it just becomes runnable.
So let's say, it's running again.
Run methods called and now it attempts
to access a so-called guarded resource
such as the intrinsic lock that's
part of every Java object.
We'll talk more about that later.
So it tries to do that,
it tries to enter a synchronized method or
a synchronized block.
And if that is in use,
that will cause it to become blocked.
In which case,
it will remain blocked until it is able
to acquire the resource that it needs.
And once it becomes acquiring
the resource, like it grabs the lock, it's
not ready to run again and the scheduler
will start at running at some point.
It then may also call
the cond.wait() method, which is
wait method that's part of the condition
that's part of every Java object.
We'll talk more about that shortly,
as well and
that causes it to go into the waiting
state and it remains in that state and
becomes deactivated Until
someone notifies it.
So it notifies it either by calling notify
or by calling notifyAll and that will wake
it up, put it back in the runnable and
then it can start to run again.
While it's running, if it terminates for
some reason, either it decides it's done
and it exits the run method or
an exception has occurred.
Either one, it then transitions
to the terminated state.
And from that point on,
it can be basically shut down.
Let's go a little bit deeper now talking
about how we start and stop Java threads.
So we'll begin by discussing
how we start a Java thread.
So starting a Java thread involves
some very interesting design and
implementation issues.
Calling start() on a thread, causes it
to start executing its run hook method.
And this actually triggers many,
many steps in the Java middleware,
virtual machine, and
operating system layer.
And if you're running on Android, there's
even a few more steps involved as well.
So the key thing to note here,
I'm about to talk about these steps,
but the key thing to remember is that
starting a thread consumes
a non-trivial amount of resources.
So you've got to be prepared to understand
that you don't want to start threads just
haphazardly, you want to do it for
a reason and
usually that reason is you've got some
fairly long running computations that
make it worthwhile to start the threads.
You can go here and
find all the Java source code.
This is sort of my shorthand to say,
here's the link and
then just replace this part
here with the session number.
Which in this case, would be 003 for this
current session that'll be how you can
find that particular location
after you find the source code for
all of the things you're
about to talk about.
So let's say, a thread says,
myThread.start().
Underneath the hood, that will then
call down to the Thread.start method,
which is part of Java and that will
then call into the virtual machine.
Thread create method,
which is a native method.
That on Android,
then calls into another native method
that's part of the Android runtime.
If you're using Dalvik, it's part of
the Dalvik runtime or if you're using Art,
it's part of the Art runtime and so on and
this would be a native method call and
then that will call even further
down to some other methods.
And then finally, these methods
will call the underlying Linux,
Android, pthread_create method.
And pthread_create as we can see here,
passes in some instructions to say,
how to start the thread.
And it passes in a method
called interpThreadStart and
interpThreadStart is actually c
function pointer that'll be used
as the entry point into the new thread
that's being created with the runtime
thread stack that was created by
the operating system in virtual machine.
InterpThreadStart in turn is
an Android internal method that
turns around and
calls backup to your code.
And finally,
the run hook method is called back on the
object that invoked start to begin with.
So as you can see, it is a whole bunch
of steps that are going on here.
And your mileage may vary a little bit
if you run a different operating system
besides Android or if you run a different
version of Android that I'm showing here.
There may be a few minor differences, but
the basic overall flow will be more or
less the same.
Let's now start discussing
how we stop Java threads and
we're going to see there's a couple of
different ways to stop Java threads.
So as it turns out,
stopping Java threads is a lot more
complicated than starting them.
And for those of you who have ever watched
the famous Disney movie, Fantasia.
There's a great clip called
The Sorcerer's Apprentice and
it illustrates the complexity of trying
to stop things once they're in motion.
So if you replace threads
with broomsticks,
you'll have basically the idea that's
going on with The Sorcerer's Apprentice.
The Sorcerer's Apprentice, which is Mickey
Mouse creates a bunch of broomsticks to do
the work for him and then the broomsticks
turn out to be very hard to shut down.
So that's kind of the metaphor to think
about as we're discussing these features.
It turns out that there's no
way in Java to safely and
involuntarily stop a Java thread, you
can't do that and there's a description
here why this is such a thorny
problem in the Java concurrency model.
So what that means is if you want
to have operations that run for
a long time in a separate thread,
they have to be coded specifically
to stop themselves voluntarily.
So there's one way to do
this is to use a stop flag.
So here's an example where we've got
a class called MyRunnable that implements
Runnable.
We've got a method called run,
we've got a loop in here that's
checking some long running operation.
As you can see here, what we do is we have
a volatile Boolean called mIsStopped.
It's set to false initially and
as long as it's not true, we keep running.
And as you can see,
this is defined as volatile.
You can take a look at this link for
more information about volatile.
In a nutshell, a volatile is
a type qualifier that indicates in
Java that any changes to that
variable are consistently and
visibly propagated to
other threads atomically.
So an easy way to think about this
is irrespective of whether or
not you have a multi-core or
multi-processor machine with different
memory that's local to each core or
processor when you use of a volatile
variable, whatever you read and
write to it, it bypasses any caches that
you may have in a core or processor and
goes directly to the global memory and it
reads or writes directly to global memory.
So that makes it certain that
the information is propagated
consistently and
visibly to other threads atomically.
We also add a method called stopMe,
that sets mIsStopped to true.
And when mIsStopped is set to true,
then the thread down here that's
running run will detect that as
long as it remembers to check whether
mIsStopped is true or is not true.
If you don't have that check there,
of course, you'll keep running for
an indefinite period of time,
which is not at all what you want to do.
So this solution using volatile
variables is very, very lightweight, but
it's not integrated into
the underlying Java virtual machine.
Which is somewhat problematic,
because certain things can't be tested for
this way.
In particular,
any blocking operations, reads,
blocking rates, weights, joins, sleeps.
All those other things won't be awakened
by the means we just described here,
which could impede the shutdown
processing in your applications for
a very long period of time.
So that's not a good way to go.
Now let's talk about how to stop Java
threads using interrupt request.
A thread can be stopped by calling its
interrupt method and you can read more
about interrupt here and I'll explain the
key points, but it's really good idea to
read the documentation,
because it's kind of subtle.
When you call interrupt,
this posts something called
an interrupt request to a thread.
And interrupts are implemented
by an internal
flag that's called
the interrupt status flag.
And when you invoke Thread.interrupt()
that sets the flag.
So, that sets the flag or
whatever thread you've just interrupted.
There are two different accessor methods
that can be used to check this flag and
each one has different side
effects on the status.
The is interrupted method as we'll see,
just checks and does not clear the status.
The interrupted method checks and
clears the status and sometimes,
it's confusing to know which one to use.
We'll talk about that in a second.
Here's a very simple program that starts,
runs and interrupts a background thread.
So we have a main program here, which
goes ahead and creates a new Thread t1.
And it does a bunch of work, we'll look
at that in a second and it's runnable.
And then down here, we start the thread,
which we'll go ahead and
follow those steps we discussed earlier
and then the run method will be called and
it'll start to do work.
It'll loop around and do stuff and calling
these methods, we'll look at more in
detail in a second and
that'll start running in the background.
And at some point,
the main thread will decide it wants to
interrupt the background thread and so
we'll take a look and
see what happens when that occurs.
Internally, the run method of
the background thread calls methods that
have to check periodically to see if the
thread that is running has been stopped.
So there's a couple of
different options here.
Let's take a look at both options.
If you have threads that block in
various library calls and system calls,
then those library calls,
assistant calls will automatically
check to see if whether or
not the interrupt has occurred and
will take the appropriate reaction,
typically through an exception.
So here's an example where you
might call sleep or wait or
certain kinds of blocking I/O calls or
join, etc.
These are all things that block and
the operating system,
the Java virtual machine will
automatically detect when that thread has
been interrupted and it'll end up
generating interrupted exception,
which you're then obliged to catch and
do something with to clean things up.
So for blocking operations,
that's the way you do it.
For non-blocking operations,
you have to periodically check to see if
the interrupt has been called,
if thread interrupt has been called.
Better to fix the bugs now and
get them into the updated slide
deck than have them lurk around.
So [COUGH] if a thread
interrupt has been called,
then there's a couple ways to check.
One way to do this is to call
Thread.interrupted and Thread.interrupted
returns true, if an interrupt request
has been received by the thread.
And whenever you call it,
it clears the interrupt status, so
it's only good to call that one time.
And a typical thing to do,
if you're interrupted is to
throw the interrupted exception.
Another thing you can do is you can use
the isInterrupted method and this method
has to be called on a specific thread,
you can't call it on a static method,
you have to call it on
a specific instance of a thread.
And this returns true,
if an interrupt request has been received.
However, it doesn't clear the interrupt
status, so that status is
still available and you can come back and
call this method multiple times.
All of these methods can actually be
overridden and you'll actually see,
if you take a look at various
other parts of the course,
you'll see some examples of this,
but it's rather rare and
you have to really know what you're doing
in order to override the methods here.
Here's a link that you can read more
about how and when you should do this.
So here's a few things to remember when
we talk about interrupting Java threads.
Java thread interrupts don't behave
like traditional hardware or
operating system interrupts.
You can read more about
what an interrupt is here.
They're actually quite different.
The Java interrupts are delivered
synchronously and non-preemptively,
which means that the thread has
to be prepared to handle them.
They don't just get
handled asynchronously.
In contrast, hardware interrupts or
more traditional Unix signals,
which are basically
software-like interrupts.
Those types of interrupts
are asynchronous and preemptive.
So you'd have no choice often,
but to handle them.
In contrast, Java thread interrupts
are not asynchronous and
they are not preemptive.
Therefore, you have to test for
them explicitly.
And usually, you throw the interrupted
exception and that's thrown
synchronously and must be handled
synchronously by the calling thread or
by the calling logic in the thread
that's throwing the exception.
There's a number of patterns for
dealing with Java thread,
InterruptedException and so
you'd take a look at this link here.
There's a number of things you can do to
program it, program exceptions properly.
One thing to do is just simply make
the interrupted exception be part of
the exception specifier on a method and
don't worry about it and
just let the caller of the method
be responsible for handling it.
So that's one approach.
So the caller or callers must then
handle the exception properly,
you'll see lots of examples of
that as we go through the course.
Another thing to do is to
catch the exception and
then perform some specific cleanup
operation and then re-throw it.
So here's an example where we're waiting
for something and if an interrupt occurs,
we want to clear out some information
that we stored in the queue and
then re-throw the exception.
The idea here is to avoid
leaking resources or
leaving the resources in
an inconsistent state.
Yet, another thing to do is
to catch an exception and
then restore the interrupt exception
status by calling interrupt again.
That way,
even if you're not going to handle it,
you can push it up a bit to the caller
to know that something has occurred.
And this basically preserves evidence
that the exception occurred for
higher levels of the call stacks, if they
knew that something was interrupted.
Portable solutions for
Java thread programming require
cooperation to stop threads.
Threads have to check periodically
to see if they've been told to stop.
This is rather fragile unfortunately,
because all parts of a program have
to follow consistent usages patterns.
You can read more about this problem in
this link and even though it tricky and
voluntary and tedious and error prone,
it's the way to go to stop Java threads.
So you have to understand
how these things work.
Let's take a quick look of an example
of how to use Java thread interrupts.
So this particular example,
you can get this from this website,
you can take a look at the code.
We're not going to look at the code right
now in detail, but I'll just outline it,
because it's very simple.
This is a program that starts,
it has a main thread that starts a
background thread that's going to compute
the greatest common divisor in
the background for random numbers.
And the run hook method that's
running in the background thread
checks periodically to see
if it's been interrupted,
because there's no blocking calls that
are being made in the run method.
It's just doing computation, it's not
doing calls that are going to block.
The main thread of control sleeps for
about four seconds and
then it sends an interrupt
to the background thread.
And when the interrupt is sent,
then of course,
the background thread will detect this and
check to see if it's been interrupted and
then it'll go ahead and
exit when it has been interrupted.