So the second part of the Java
built-in monitor object lecture
will go a little further and
focus on the coordination aspects that
are provided by Java monitor objects.
In particular, we'll talk specifically
about the notify and wait mechanisms.
So there's a couple pieces to this.
If you recall our earlier discussion,
Java synchronized methods and
synchronized statements only
provide a partial solution.
And to avoid this, there are some
additional features that are provided that
help to coordinate interactions, and
these are the wait, notify,
and notifyAll methods.
These methods are defined
on Java object itself.
Wait is used to cause the current thread
to wait until another thread invokes
the notify method or
the notifyAll method for an object.
Notify is used to wake up a single
thread that's waiting on the monitor.
And notifyAll is used to wake up
all the threads that are waiting
on the object's monitor.
So this wakes up one, this wakes up all.
And we'll talk later about why you
would use one versus the other.
Each Java monitor object has
an entrance queue and a wait queue.
I talked about this before.
You can read about this
in the Wikipedia links.
And so when you go into a monitor object,
you initially start out in the entrance
queue if there's other threads
that are there waiting.
And while you're running,
you can decide to wait, in which case
you temporarily step outside
of the critical section and
you wait on the wait queue for your chance
to go back in to the critical section.
So, we use the entrance queue
to serialize thread access
to the monitor object's critical section.
And any time you call wait,
that's done on the wait queue.
When you call notify or notifyAll on
an object, that also applies to the wait
queue by waking up one or all threads
that are currently waiting on that queue.
So here's some simple examples.
This is now, now we have a new
class called SimpleBlockingQueue.
And SimpleBlockingQueue is going to fix
the problems we had with the earlier
implementation that was either the buggy
queue or the busy synchronized queue.
So what's going to happen here is whenever
you call put, we're going to go ahead and
check to see if the queue is full.
If the queue is full, we're going to
wait for the queue to be not full.
So that's a way to put ourselves to sleep
when we can't make forward progress.
When wait is called, and this is very
important, it atomically releases
the intrinsic lock, which was acquired
because this was a synchronized method,
and then it goes ahead and
sleeps on the object's wait queue.
So the object that's an instance
of simple blocking queue,
this wait call will release the lock and
then go to sleep on the wait queue.
This implements what's called
the guarded suspension pattern,
and we'll talk more about that later.
When we finally get a chance to go ahead
because the queue is no longer full,
we add an item to the queue and
then we go ahead and we notify
anybody who's waiting that the queue
is no longer going to be empty.
So this is a way to notify everybody that
there's something changed in the queue.
And that'll wake up all of the threads
that are blocked on the weight q.
Now this actually turns out to
be somewhat problematic for
a variety of reasons having
to do with performance.
But that's why Java also supports
something called condition
objects which we wont talk
much about in this MOOC,
but is available in other
videos on my website.
We'll talk more about quit and take later.
Okay.
So that's the basic mechanism.
Under the hood, these monitor objects
are implemented using POSIX mechanisms.
POSIX is the portable operating system for
UNIX that defines a standard way
of interacting with hardware in
operating systems like SOLARIS,
or Linux, implement POSIX.
And so the entrance queue into a monitor
object is implemented in Android and
in most Java implementations with
something called a POSIX mutex,
which is a mutual exclusion lock that
supports recursive locking semantics.
And you can read more about mutexes here.
Likewise, wait queues can be
implemented with something called POSIX
condition variables.
And you can read more about them there.
They basically allow multiple
threads to queue up waiting for
a chance to access some
resource that's controlled
via a condition expression using
the guarded suspension pattern.
And they're very similar
to Java ConditionObjects.
We'll talk about them a little bit later,
but they're better found other
places besides this MOOC.
Okay.
Let's take a look now at how the simple
blocking queue example works.
We're going to look at it first
from a visual point of view,
then we're going to look
at the source code.
So, first we're going to take a look,
you can see that the source
code is here at this link, and
we're going to zoom in and kind of look
at how it's going to work visually.
We're going to have a queue of threads
that can block on the monitor locks
entrance queue, and
another queue of threads that can wait
on the monitor conditions wait queue.
So let's take a look.
Let's say we have the situation
where we're going to try to take
an element out of the queue.
And let's say for sake of argument
that the queue is empty to begin with.
So, somebody calls take,
that causes the monitor object
to go into the region up
here by the entrance queue.
Since there's nobody else there,
we acquire the lock.
That thread is now running in the critical
section of the simple blocking
queue object.
And then it goes and it checks to see
whether or not the list is empty.
Because the list is empty, we're going to
assume that it's going to have to block.
So it's cause wait.
And then that causes it to atomically
release the intrinsic lock and
then go block on the monitor conditions.
So this thread is now over here blocked,
it's stepped outside the critical section
and it's waiting to re-enter
the critical section when it's notified.
Now, another thread comes along,
thread T2.
And this thread is going to be
putting stuff into the queue.
So, it's going to be putting something in.
So, it comes in,
it enters the monitor object,
there's nobody else there,
it acquires the monitor intrinsic lock and
it goes ahead and it adds an item to
the queue and then it calls notifyAll.
And notifyAll, as we'll see in a second,
is going to wake up this
waiting thread over here, T1.
So after it notifies, it then releases
the lock and it exits the monitor object.
At that point, because it notified
thread T1, T1 wakes up and
it unblocks on the monitor condition, and
then it goes and it tries to re-enter
the critical section which is protected by
the entrance queue and the intrinsic lock.
If there was something else already there,
it would have to wait.
If there's nothing else there,
it can re-acquire the lock,
re-enter the critical section.
And now it'll decide, it'll detect that
the queue has actually got an element
in it, and so it will be able to
remove the element from the queue, and
then return and release the lock and
exit the monitor object.
So those are the basic steps
that are going on there.
Here's the same thing, except we're
going to look at this from a code
perspective as opposed to
a visualization perspective.
Once again,
you can grab the implementation here,
there's a couple different
places you can get it.
We have an internal state that has to
be protected against race conditions.
The constructor sets that state.
We could make this,
these could be final if we wanted to.
And then, the thread can wait for
a condition in a synchronized methods.
So here is the synchronized
method called take,
and this uses the guarded
suspension pattern.
Take is going to acquire the monitor
lock and wait while the queue is empty.
So, it comes in here,
it gets the intrinsic lock, and
it checks to see if the queue is empty or
not.
Let's say for the sake of argument
the queue is empty, we then have to wait.
Wait will atomically release the lock and
go to sleep.
You almost always, not always, but almost
always, want to call wait in a loop.
And that's because when you're awakened,
when somebody notifies you,
the condition you're waiting on may or
may not be true.
So you always have to re-check it.
When wait returns, it automatically
acquires the intrinsic lock.
And therefore,
whenever you check this condition,
this condition is always checked with
the lock held, the intrinsic lock held.
So the waiting thread can't assume that
the notification it receives is for
its condition, so it has to do the check.
You can read more about these
situations in the cases here.
The thread that's blocking in wait won't
continue until another thread notifies it
that the condition may be true.
So here's an example of
where that would happen.
So, here's take.
Now we're in put.
In put you can see that we've
blocked while the queue is full.
And we check to see whether something's
full by checking the capacity.
And if it's not full,
we add the message and we notify.
So that call to notify here
will then notify everybody.
Now, this is actually a limitation from
Java monitor objects which have the weird
quirk that there's only one monitor
condition for each monitor object.
That's the reason why Java also supports
something called condition object
which we'll briefly mention later, but are
really outside the scope of this class.
So, once notifyAll is called, that will
cause the thread that's blocked in wait
to wake up, and it'll re-acquire the lock,
re-evaluate the condition.
And then it'll go ahead and continue,
and it'll remove the item from the list.
And it will call notifyAll to let anybody
know that the queue is no longer full.
And it releases the lock when it returns.
Those are the basic steps.
That's just showing you how you
typically program this kind of code.
It's very stylistic or idiomatic.
It always looks pretty much the same.
And the other thing to note
is that people typically
don't program to this
type of code directly.
They build library interfaces,
or frameworks,
to encapsulate the complexities of
programming at this level of abstraction.
So, I'm just showing you how it works
under the hood so you'll be aware of it.
But in practice you may not program
this level very much because you would
want to build abstractions that shield
developers from these complexities.
So let's talk about some of the traps and
pitfalls of using Java
built in monitor objects.
There's a bunch of things you have
to be aware of to use them properly.
As I mentioned before,
there's only one wait queue and
one entrance queue per monitor object.
And you can read about the problems with
this in a paper I wrote many years ago.
The big problem is something
called nested monitor lockout.
Nested monitor lockout occurs
because the outermost method
will aquire the intrinsic lock.
And then if you call into a nested object,
that intrinsic lock will still be held and
therefore other methods to try to call on
the class will not be able to access them.
So, that can lead to tricky problems
that are described in this tutorial that
are worth knowing about.
You have to be very,
very careful with nested monitor lockout.
The Java monitor objects.
Then, there is also the fact
that monitor locks lack certain
features that are provided
by ReentrantLock.
So there's another class in
Java called a ReentrantLock
which gives you more features.
For example,
its supports conditional locking,
timed conditional locking, and the ability
to lock in a way that's interruptible.
Whereas the built-in synchronized
methods and synchronized statements
are not interruptible and
cannot be acquired conditionally.
So those are some lacks of
features in the built-in stuff.
And Java ReentrantLock adds
that additional capability.
And some other problems.
There's some subtleties associated
with using notify versus notifyAll.
There's a good set of discussions here
on this stack overflow article that
talk about the trade offs
between the two methods.
As a general rule, you can only
use notify in certain situations.
And those situations are in situations
where there's uniform waiters,
that means all waiters always are waiting
for the same condition expression.
And the reason for this is there's
only one condition per wait cue.
And the other thing is, you could
only do this if each thread executes
the same logic after the wait returns.
So, as a result, if you used monitor
objects and built-in monitor objects
in Java, then you typically have to use
notify all because oftentimes they wait on
multiple conditions such as the queue
being empty and the queue being full.
There's also some fairness
issues related to the order
in which threads are notified.
By default, the semantics of Java
are so-called haphazard notification.
And so, to avoid haphazard notification
you can apply the specific notification
pattern, which you can read about
here at this link on my website,
which is a paper that describes how
to do specific notification in Java.
Basically, specific notification
allows you to have the implementation
choose which thread to run
based on certain properties,
like how long it's been in the queue or
its priority, etc.
As a rule of thumb,
the built-in Java monitor object
mechanisms we talked about are very
popular and efficient and common.
But if you do really
sophisticated concurrency control
you're going to need more.
And so you really need to understand Java
util concurrent and java util concurrent
locks, which is a bit outside the scope
of this MOOC, but if you're just doing
android programming, what we've covered
here so far is probably sufficient.
If you're doing Java programming,
especially Java server-side programming,
then you really need to understand
these more powerful mechanisms.
Android provides a whole bunch
of concurrency frameworks,
which we're going to talk
about starting next week,
which overcome the limitations
with these low-level Java
mechanisms when applied in the context
of the Android development environment.
And so we'll see that there's a couple
of different frameworks we're going to
talk about later.
There's something that's
called the handlers, messages,
and runnables framework,
or the hammer framework.
And there's also something
called the async task framework.
And both of those topics will be
covered beginning in week two.
If you want to know a bit more about
those topics feel free to go ahead and
watch the material that's available on
the pre-recorded, supplemental lectures.