So today we're going to
talk about Java semaphores.
And we're going to talk about
the structure and functionality of
the semaphores and show some examples
of how they can be applied in practice.
So the first thing that we'll
talk about is, explain how Java
semaphores can enable multiple threads
through a couple of different things.
Number one, immediate access to
a limited number of shared resources,
that's one way they're used, and
another way they're used is to coordinate
the order in which operations occur.
So a semaphore can be viewed as a
mechanism for atomically incrementing and
decrementing an integer count to
control access to a shared resource.
The terminology itself came from
signaling mechanisms that were used for
ships and railroads and so on.
And in particular, semaphores are used to
control access to a shared railroad track.
So if you live in countries that
have railroads that are widely used,
you know that it's sometimes necessary
to single-track the trains for
various reasons.
And semaphores are used in order to
control access to that track by multiple
trains so
they don't interfere with each other.
In the software world,
we use semaphores to control access and
mediate the interactions
between multiple threads.
So, for example,
you might have a resource pool
where you wanted to gauge or provide
access to a limited number of threads,
even though there might actually be
multiple threads that are able to run.
So you might say,
we'll give a semaphore with a kind of two,
and we'll have a whole pool of threads try
to access whatever resource is protected
by the semaphore, and
as long as the count is greater than zero,
then a thread can acquire a semaphore and
do its thing.
But when the count drops to zero, then any
other threads are going to have to wait.
They're going to be blocked.
And we'll see some
examples of this shortly.
There are a couple of
different types of semaphores.
There's so-called counting semaphores,
which have a number of states that
are defined by a counter variable.
Sometimes these states
are referred to as permits.
And this counter variable
has a precise meaning.
So if the count of states or
the permits is negative,
then that many threads are queued
waiting to acquire the semaphore.
If the count is zero,
that means there's no waiting threads, and
an acquire operation would
be put in the queue and
blocked until the counter of
the permits or states is positive.
And finally, if the value of the semaphore
is positive, then there are no waiting
threads, and an acquire operation
will not block the invoking thread.
So those are the three main categories
of states for counting semaphores.
Then there's also something
called binary semaphores,
which are basically either all or nothing.
They have two states only,
acquired and not acquired.
And that restricts the counter
to the values zero or one.
Now, it turns out in practice, of course,
that you can typically emulate a binary
semaphore with a counting semaphore
just by constraining its values
to be zero or one by convention.
We're going to show examples
of both counting and
binary semaphores in later videos.
One thing we'll take a look at is we'll
take a look at this Palantir, Palantir
manager application, which is actually
your first programming assignment.
We'll talk about that.
And then we'll also talk about a
concurrent ping-pong application, and I'll
show you the code for that, which uses
semaphores in a slightly different way.
So let's take a look at a simple example.
So consider some kind of image-rendering
application that uses a pool of threads to
process different parts of the images
concurrently on multiple cores.
That's what the apples here are.
These are cores.
That's the intent of the image there.
So we're going to configure
the application to restrict the number of
threads that can run concurrently
on the processor cores to avoid
taking all the cores on the device for
image processing and saving a few for
other things like email or web browsing or
watching videos or whatever.
So for sake of argument, we'll say that
we're only going to allow two cores
to enable the rest of
the system to be responsive.
So even though there are four cores,
we're only going to allow two
to be used for image processing.
So in that case, we would create
a semaphore, a counting semaphore,
with a count of two.
And a permit has to be acquired from
the semaphore before the thread can run.
And so in this case,
one thread comes along,
it acquires a permit, the semaphore
account is decremented by one.
Another thread comes along,
it acquires a permit,
the semaphore account
is decremented by one.
But any other threads that come
along while the count is zero or
less need to block until one of
the other threads releases the permit.
So if another thread releases the permit,
then another thread can take it and
start to run.
This is an example of a so-called
fully-bracketed model of acquiring and
releasing permits to a semaphore.
And in a fully-bracketed model,
the thread that acquires the semaphore
is also the thread to release it.
There are other models as well where
instead of having fully-bracketed models,
you can have a model where the thread
that acquires a semaphore is
not the thread to release it.
And we'll see an example of that later
when we talk about the concurrent
ping-pong application.
There's a number of interesting
human known uses of semaphores.
My favorite actually came from some
experience that I had when I was at
the University of California Irvine
as a graduate student.
And in those days, we had a situation
where we wanted to spend all of our time
playing volleyball at the beach.
So there would be volleyball
courts at the beach, and
invariably there would always
be more people, more teams,
who wanted to play volleyball than there
were courts available to play volleyball.
So the way it worked was that we
had a bag of beach volleyballs and
there was one volleyball for
every court that was available.
And the protocol was that if
a team wanted to play volleyball,
it would send somebody
to the bag of balls.
And if there was a ball available in
the bag of balls, then the person could
retrieve that and then their team
could play on one of the courts.
If there was no ball in the bag of balls,
then the person had to wait until one
of the other teams, pair of teams,
finished, and then they would be obliged
to return the ball back to the bag.
So as long as the number of courts
available matched the number of
semaphores, or
beach volleyballs in the bag,
then we had an easy way of being able to
know whether you could play right away or
whether you had to wait until
there was a court available.
So that was basically the way that we
used semaphores to play volleyball
in grad school.
Let's take a look at Java semaphores.
Java semaphores are a variant
of counting semaphores.
They have some interesting
characteristics we'll talk about shortly.
You can read more about them here.
They don't actually implement any
synchronization-related interfaces.
Unlike other mechanisms in Java,
synchronizers like Java CountDownLatches
or Java ReentrantLocks or
ReentrantReadWriteLocks or so on,
the semaphores don't implement
synchronization-related interfaces.
Under the hood, they apply a pattern
from the so-called Gang of Four book,
the design pattern catalog,
which you can read about on the FAQ.
And they applied the pattern
called the bridge pattern,
which you can read more about here.
The bridge pattern essentially
decouples an interface from multiple
implementations, and it's used in
the context of semaphore to allow fair and
non-fair semantics of the semaphore to
be supported by a common interface.
And we'll talk more about
that in just a minute.
Here's how this works.
There's a private field called Sync, which
is an instance of base class called Sync.
Kind of a funny name.
In the bridge pattern, that plays
the role of the implementor hierarchy.
Then there's a, subclass,
the subclass sync as an abstract
class extends a class in Java called
AbstractQueuedSynchronizer, which
you can read about here.
The AbstractQueuedSynchronizer is
a framework that's used by many
synchronizers in java,
javautil.concurrent so.
ReentrantLock, ReentrantReadWriteLock,
Semaphore,
Countdown latches a bunch of things
that use abstract queued synchronizer to
basically coordinate FIFO
access to some count.
In this case it would
be the semaphore count.
So the sync class is the base class or
the super class.
And then we have a couple of sub
classes called fair sync and
non fair sync [NOISE].
And we'll see how those
are used in a second.
The fair and non-fair sync are used
to implement either a fair or
non-fair lock acquisition model.
So, by default, you have,
by default this is the default
semaphore up here, this one.
The one that just has one
parameter called permits.
By default, the Semaphore uses what's
called non-fair sync semantics,
which means that it's up to the hardware
and the virtual machine to pick, whichever
Semaphore will be whichever thread
that's waiting will be released when and
given the chance to acquire a Semaphore
whenever the Semaphore is released.
That's non-fair, and it's meant
to optimize hardware performance.
Then there's also something
called FairSync, and
if you use this version of the Semaphore,
the one that takes the fair parameter,
then if fair is set to true, then
the FairSync semantics will be selected.
And FairSync basically allows for the,
basically FIFO access to the semaphore
values by waiting threads.
So whichever thread has been waiting
the longest will be the one that
will be released next when
a thread releases the semaphore.
So the thread that's been waiting the
longest will acquire the 7411 is released
and there's a bunch of trade offs there
that we'll talk about in a little bit.
The bottom line is that the not fair or
non-fair sync semantics are much
more efficient than the point of view of
releasing the waiting threads quickly,
whereas the fair sync semantics
are not as efficient, but
they give you FIFO ordering, which means
you don't have to worry about starvation.
Which is a problem where one thread
never gets the semaphore, or
doesn't get the semaphore for a long time
because it's always given to someone else.
Turns out that there's other parts of Java
synchronizers that use a similar model and
use a similar pattern,
like the Java ReentrantLock, for example.
And the Java ReentrantReadWriteLock.
The constructors create a semaphore
with a given number of permits, so
you can see here that you can
give the permit count, and
the count is not a maximum,
it's just an initial value.
So you could actually
have the count go above
the permit count that's given to
the constructor, that's perfectly legal.
But the original count is just
the default starting point.
And ironically the permanent
value can actually be negative.
You can actually get a minus one or
a minus two, or whatever,
some negative number as the permit count.
And only until the permit is
released that number of times will
the waiting threads be
able to make progress.
And this is typically used to
coordinate the order in which,
the time that which threads start to run.
Let's talk a bit more about some
other methods in Semaphore.
There's a bunch of methods that
are part of the public interface
which includes acquire.
Acquire uninterruptibly,
try acquire, and release.
And all these methods simply forward to
the implementation or implementer methods
that are defined as part of the bridge
pattern implementer hierarchy.
So here's an example of acquire.
Acquire obtains a single
permit from the semaphore.
And it will block until one is available.
And under the hood it's implementation
calls aquireSharedInterruptibly(1).
And that uses the abstract
cued synchronizer framework to
basically get it one permit.
AcquireUninterruptibly does
much the same thing.
But unlike acquire, acquireUninterruptibly
will ignore interrupts.
If an interrupt occurs, then it simply
going to be ignored and it'll continue
to block until the interrupt is
[INAUDIBLE] semaphore's available.
TryAcquire() is used to obtain a permit,
if one is available when you
invoke the tryAcquire() method.
It's basically a conditional acquire.
If there's no semaphore available,
then it returns false.
If there is a semaphore available,
it gets it right away.
And ironically, the non-timed tryAcquire()
doesn't honor, the fairness setting.
It'll just go ahead and barge in, and
take the semaphore even if there's
other waiters that are blocked.
If you want to have a tryAcquire()
that doesn't work that way,
you can use the timed tryAquire()
that we'll talk about later.
Release returns a permit and it increases
the count of the semaphore by one.
And you can see again it just
forwards to the underlying
abstract queue synchronizer
framework to release one semaphore.
It's valid for the permit count to
exceed the initial permit count.
That's not a problem.
Moreover, it's also,
as I mentioned before possible for
the, the value of a semaphore
to be negative initially.
And, and all that means is that until
someone calls release enough times for
the value to become greater then zero,
anybody who's trying to acquire
this Semaphore will have to wait.
So that's what a negative value means,
as the initial value.
So it just means that somebody has
got to release enough times to
get the value over zero, in order for
anybody to make forward progress.
And again, that's typically used for
things like test programs to
start up a bunch of threads.
And then they all wait to acquire
the Semaphores, and then they go ahead and
release them.
Okay, so let's go ahead and
continue discussing.
There's actually a whole pile
of other Semaphore methods.
There's acquire [NOISE], and
acquire uninterruptedly.
TryAcquire and release, all of which
take different numbers of permits.
So you can see here, you can
actually block to acquire n-permits
like where N is three, or five, or
ten, or whatever that number is, and
you'll only return when
all N are available.
In contrast, by default acquire and
release acquire or
release a single permit.
And then there's also methods
that will be timed out.
They will do conditional acquisition of
semaphores, but they'll only block for
a certain amount of time.
And if they don't get the semaphore in
that amount of time, or the number of
semaphores they request in that amount
of time, then they go ahead and return.
So here's a good time to talk about
what happens if you need more than one
semaphore, so if you call
acquire with a count of two, and
there's only one semaphore available,
then acquire will block until there
are at least two semaphores available.
So that way you can make sure you get
both semaphores before you return.
Ironically the timed tryAcquire() methods
do honor the fairness setting, so
they don't actually barge in.
If you call a timed tryAcquire(),
and there are other Semaphores that
are waiting, and
the fairness semantics are set to fair,
Then you will simply wait
at the end of the queue.
Either to get the semaphore or
until your timeout period elapses.
Now as we talked about before,
the image processing example I mentioned
before was an example where you're going
to have acquisition basically doing
what's called a fully bracketed protocol.
The thread that acquires it,
is the one that releases it.
But there are other situations
where acquiring and
releasing permanence to a semaphore
don't have to be fully bracketed.
So, we'll talk shortly about a ping
pong example, where the ping and
the pong threads take turns
printing ping or pong.
And they use basically binary
semaphores in order to be able to
release each other in the proper order.
So semaphores can be used to coordinate
the order in which things occur.
Speaking of which, let's go ahead and
talk about this example.
So this is the ping pong example,
you can go here to this link.
You'll find that all
the examples in the slides
have a corresponding URL
where you can find the code.
And so, that's where you would go to find
it, this is the ping pong console example.
And you'll see that sometimes the code
examples don't appear in
the POSA-15 directory.
Sometimes they appear other places.
And rather than try to copy them
around and keep them all in sync,
I just give the URL wherever can you
find them in my GitHub repositories.
So they're always available.
They should always be noted on the slides,
and
all you have to do is just click them
when I upload the slides on the PDF.
So this particular
application is kind of fun.
It coordinates thread interactions
by a Java semaphores.
And in this case the threads alternate,
putting Ping and Pong on the console.
So if things are done properly, when you
run the program, it should say Ping(1),
Pong(1), Ping(2), Pong(2),
Ping(3), Pong(3), and so on.
And then the numbers here are basically
the iterations that are taking place.
If you don't do this correctly,
then it'll say all the Pings first,
followed by all the Pongs, or
it'll do them out of order or something.
So, that would be bad.
So we're going to use binary
semaphores to make this all work.
Here are the various classes.
In this example, I'll first give you
sort of an overview of the design, and
then we'll go and
take a look at the Implementation.
So, we have a java class
called PlayPingPong,
which is going to have a nested
PingPongThread inside of it.
And PlayPingPong has a constructor
that takes the number
of iterations to run, and it has a run()
method so it's going to be its own thread.
And you go ahead and run this thing, and
the run() method here will go ahead and
create a couple of PingPongThreads.
And those PingPongThreads will be used
in order to actually run the protocol
to play ping-pong by taking turns
acquiring and releasing the semaphore.
And there's actually two semaphores.
There's a first semaphore and
a second semaphore.
And the threads take turns, basically
acquiring and releasing the semaphore,
in order to get the alternating
printing behavior that we need here.
We also have a couple other things.
We have an Options() class that
controls stuff like the number of
iterations to run.
And we also have a Main program that
makes an instance of PlayPingPong.
Here's an interaction diagram that
illustrates basically how this works.
The main program starts to run and
when it's run,
it goes ahead and it creates a ping.
A PingPongThread for the ping object and
a PingPong instance called pong.
So we have ping and pong.
Both of these are threads.
So we go ahead and
create them and start them.
And when they start to run,
they take turns doing the following.
The ping thread will first
acquire the first semaphore,
it will then print Ping, and
it will then release the second semaphore.
And, the pong thread will block
acquiring the second semaphore, and
it will print Pong, and
then it will release the first semaphore.
So you'll see that these are going to
alternate going back and forth.
Acquiring or
releasing each other's semaphore in order
to get the correct alternate behavior.
And so the semaphores here, are used to
coordinate the order in which ping and
pong are called.
And as we'll see,
they're going to use basically counting
semaphores with a count of zero or one.
And they're going to
take turns doing that.
The main thread of
control will simply wait
to do a various synchronization to join
on the exiting of the other two threads.
So, when the other two threads,
the ping thread and
the pong thread exit,
then the main thread will join.
And once they're joined,
then the program will go ahead and exit.
So let's take a look at the code here.
Let me go ahead and
bring up another slide,
and we will take a look at the code.
Let's see, I'm going to go ahead and
share my Emax window.
All right, so we go over here to POSA-15,
examples, PingPong, and console.
So here's the actual code for
this program.
This is just a simple Java application,
it's not an Android application.
But we also have Android versions
of this code as well, but
we'll talk about that later.
So, here's the main program,
as you can see it's very simple.
The main program goes ahead and
initializes the options singleton.
So you can have command line arguments
that will influence how the program runs.
It then creates a PlayPingPong object,
with the appropriate given
number of iterations.
And then this pingPong object is passed
to a new thread because it's a runnable.
And we start that thread, and that will
call the run hook method on PlayPingPong,
which is a runnable.
So let's go look at PlayPingPong.
Here's class PlayPingPong.
This implements Runnable.
It keeps track of the number of iterations
to alternate pinging and ponging.
It has a nested static class
called PingPongThread.
I could've moved this
class to it's own file but
I just wanted to keep this example simple.
It doesn't really matter,
in this case it's fairly concise.
So PingPongThread extends Thread,
then it keeps track of the number
of iterations to PingPong.
It keeps track of the string,
whether we're going to ping or pong.
And it keeps track of the pair of
semaphores, firstSema and secondSema.
After, it goes ahead and
initializes those fields.
And then when acquire() is called,
It will acquire the first
semaphore uninterruptibly, and
when release() is called,
it will release the second semaphore.
So notice that it's going to wait on one
semaphore, and then release the other.
And that's how we're going to
get the ping pong behavior.
Here's the run() method,
the run() method just loops for
i equals 1, <= nMaxIterations,
and every time through the loop,
it calls acquire() to get a semaphore for,
it then prints out ping or pong.
And then it releases the other
semaphore so that semaphore can run.
And then it loops back around again and
waits to acquire its semaphore again.
Here's the constructor.
It just sets nMaxIterations.
And here's the run()
method of PlayPingPong.
So what this does,
is it creates a pair of semaphores.
The pingSema starts out unlocked,
because it has a count of 1.
And the pong semaphore starts out locked,
because it has a count of zero.
And so
what that means is that the ping thread,
when it goes to acquire the semaphore,
will find that it's going to be unlocked,
so it'll get a chance to go.
But when the pong thread goes
to acquire its semaphore,
it's going to find it's got a value
of zero, so it's going to block.
Here's how we create those two threads.
Here's pingThread.
Here's pongThread.
They both are instances of PingPongThread
where you give the max iterations that
you want to loop.
You get the string to print ping or
pong, and
then you give the ping semaphore first,
in the case of the ping thread, and
the pong semaphore second,
in the case of the ping thread.
And in the case of the pong thread,
you get the pong semaphore first,
followed by the ping semaphore.
And that means that
the pingThread always starts.
We then go ahead and start both threads.
Those threads go off and run.
And then the main thread,
not the main thread.
The thread that's running here, the
PlayPingPong object thread, would go ahead
and wait for both ping and pong threads to
exit, so it does joins on both of them.
And when it's all done, we print
the fact that we're done and we exit.
So I encourage you to take a look at
this program and see how it works.
It's a fun little example
of how to use a semaphore.
And this particular example, as you can
see, does not require full bracketing.
It will just go ahead and basically
alternate printing ping and pong.
All right.
So let's go back and finish off our slides
and then we'll take some questions.
So we're going to talk now about
usage considerations for semaphores.
So semaphores are more flexible than
some of the other Java synchronizers.
In particular, it's more flexible than the
synchronized statements that we looked at
yesterday in the last class, and
it's also more flexible than
the Java Reentrant Lock.
And one of the reasons why
it's more flexible is because
it allows a non-fully-bracketed protocol.
In other words, one thread acquires,
a different thread releases,
whereas the other synchronization
mechanisms we just discussed,
synchronized statements and Reentrant
Locks require fully-bracketed protocols.
So they're only good for
certain kinds of serialization concerns.
Another thing you can do that's very
flexible with Java synchronizers is you
can acquire and release multiple
permits in a single operation.
You don't have to have the acquire and
release methods be fully bracketed,
as we just talked about.
However, when you use them to manage
access to resource pools, it's going
to track the number of free resources,
not which resources are actually free.
And so that means you have
to use some other mechanism,
such as a hash map or other semaphores or
whatever, in order to figure out
which resource is actually available.
And we'll see some examples
of that a little bit later.
Another issue with semaphores is they can
be tedious and error-prone to program due
to common traps and pitfalls with
using these low-level synchronizers.
For example,
one common mistake is to acquire
a semaphore and then forget to release it.
And this sometimes happens if you have
exceptions that get thrown inside blocks
of code and the exception handlers
don't correctly release the resource,
the semaphore that was acquired.
So it's a good idea to get into the habit
of using try-finally blocks to make sure
you always release semaphores or
locks, even if an exception is thrown.
So here's an example where
you could actually do this,
where you use a finally block in
order to release the semaphore.
But the problem that we see here is that
we're actually holding the semaphore for
a very long period of time, and we might
be doing something that doesn't involve
the semaphore so
it doesn't need to be held.
So holding a semaphore for an overly
long time is another common problem.
And then another problem is releasing the
semaphore more times than actually needed.
So here we acquire the semaphore and
then we do multiple releases.
And that'll keep incrementing
the account by one,
which may cause problems if that
resource is not actually intended to be
accessible concurrently by that
many simultaneous threads.
Sometimes calling multiple
releases is perfectly fine.
Other times, it's a bug.
So you have to be very careful in
how you reason about your program
in order to use these kinds of
locking mechanisms correctly.