The first topic we're going to
talk about here is Java threads.
And they're, of course, important as the
foundation for concurrency in Android, and
you'll also need to know something
about threads in order to do some of
the assignments in the course.
Although later in the course, we'll
be covering other Android concurrency
frameworks that alleviate the need
to know a lot about threads.
So the first thing we're going to be doing
here is we're going to be talking about
what the Java threading mechanisms are,
and
how they work to program
concurrent software.
To understand Java Threads, it helps to
understand how to program Java Threads,
and in order to do that you have to
give the thread some code to run.
And there's a couple of different ways
to give Java Threads some code to run.
One thing that you need
to do is you need to,
one way to do it is to
extend the thread class.
Thread is a class that's built
into the Java language, and so
it's always available.
And so
one thing you can do is come along and
subclass from thread, and
override the run method.
So here's a simple example.
We're going to create and start a thread
using a named subclass of a thread.
So we have a class called MyThread that
extends thread, and the method that does
the work is going to be in the run,
the Run Hook Method as it's called.
The hook method is just the method that
can be overridden by a subclass to provide
some functionality that the base class
doesn't know about how to do, but
it knows to call.
Here we go ahead and
make a new instance of MyThread, and
then we can start MyThread.
And as we'll see later,
that basically launches a new thread of
control on the virtual machine and
the underlying operating system and
then that begins to run the run hook
method that was defined earlier.
You could also do this as a one liner
using an anonymous thread instance.
So down here you could say new
MyThread.start, and that will go ahead and
start the thread to run.
A second way to run a thread,
create a thread and
make a thread run,
is to implement the runnable interface.
So, in this particular case
you're going to basically
implement a runnable and
override the run hook method.
And there's a couple of ways to do this.
One way to do this is to create and
start a thread using a named
class as the runnable.
So, here we have MyRunnable,
the implements Runnable, and
it fills in the run method.
And then down here we can say
new myRunnable and we can
then pass that runnable to a new instance
of the thread and tell that to start.
So this is an anonymous thread,
but it's a named instance
of runnable that we're instantiating
here and we're starting it.
So you can see that there's an extra step
here because we're making a runnable and
then we're giving that
runnable to the thread.
Another way to do things is to
use an anonymous inner class.
So rather than going ahead and making it
an object as we've done here and then
explicitly passing that to thread, instead
we can go ahead and say new thread.
And then inside the constructor
parameter to thread,
we make ourselves an anonymous instance
of an inner class called Anonymous or
it doesn't have a name really,
it's just an instance of a runnable.
And then we can go ahead and
override the run method and
put the code to run in here.
So this is a much more, a bit more
concise way, I guess by some definition
of concise because you don't
have to define a separate class.
So it turns out that this approach is
used very heavily in Java code and
in Android code, you'll see this used
all over the place this callbacks and
various kinds of things to
handle logic as callbacks.
If you're in a position to use Java 8,
there's a really cool extension to this.
Or, actually,
it's not really an extension,
it's actually a simplification using
something called Lambda Expressions.
And so all this complicated,
boiler plate code here disappears and
it just looks like this.
So you basically say open
close paren indicating
a method that takes no parameters.
And then you have an arrow and
then you write the code that you
want to run in the run method here.
Now unfortunately Android doesn't
really support Java 8 yet,
unless you use Retroland.
I think its called Retro Lambda and so
we're not going to do
a lot of Java 8 stuff.
I just wanted to point out that there is
some cool stuff coming down the pipe that
you can use now if you have
the ability to program Java 8, and
it makes your code a lot more concise.
So that's basically how we go ahead and
create threads by
a couple different means.
Let's not talk about how to pass
parameters to a started thread.
So the run method that's defined
in Java Thread and in Runnable
doesn't take any parameters, as you
can see, it's a no parameter method.
So how can we pass parameters to threads?
Well there are a couple of
different ways to do it.
So one way to do this is to basically
create a class constructor and
then go ahead and
have that constructor store
the information in private fields, and
then access those fields
within the run hook method.
So here's a case where we extend Runnable
or sorry we implement Runnable, and
then we add a private field.
We store that field in
the constructor of this class, and
then the run method goes ahead and
accesses that via the field.
So that's one way to do it.
Another way to do it is
to add a Setter Method.
So rather than just using a constructor,
you can also have a method
called setThreadType, or
whatever you want to call it, and
then you do the same kind of thing.
You assign the value and
then you go ahead and
use the value inside of the run method.
So those are the typical ways of getting
access to parameters that you want to pass
to a thread, since you can't pass
them to the run method directly.
Let's talk about Running Java Threads.
So, after start is called,
the underlying virtual machine and
operating system would go ahead and
create the threads resources.
And the Java virtual machine will then
call the run hook method to start
doing the work.
And this involves a number
of layers in the Java stack.
So we've got the operating system kernel
of course, and the system libraries.
These are typical written in C or C++,
usually C for the case of threads.
Then there's a Java virtual machine which
is typically written in some Java with
a lot of Native code.
And then that exposes an interface
that's used by the Thread Libraries in
Java you took concurrent.
And so those are the layers
we're talking about here.
So, when someone says new thread
that makes a new object, but
only when they call start
are the real resources
allocated by the Java virtual machine and
operating system.
And we'll talk more about that
in the next set of slides.
And once start method returns,
then run is up and running, and
then things are running concurrently.
And so the original thread that created
the new thread, and the new thread
are able to run concurrently and they're
able to block independently of each other.
Generally any thread, any code can be
run in a thread, although there are some
limitations that are typically
framework or platform specific.
So, you can do almost
everything in a run method.
However, windowing toolkits often
restrict which thread can access the GUI
components, the various things like
the views, and the dialogues, and
the widgets and so on.
Those can typically only be accessed
by the main thread of control.
And you can find out more about that
here in the context of Android,
where they talk about something called the
UI thread, or the user interface thread.
And we'll talk a lot more about
that later in the course.
As long as the run method hasn't returned,
either gracefully or
non-gracefully, the thread will
continue to live and be alive.
So, however, if it's logically alive but
of course the underlying operating
system in virtual machines scheduler can
suspend and resume a thread
many times over its lifecycle.
Put it to sleep for
reasons of being able to do preemption and
other kinds of thread scheduling
magic that the operating system does.
If you want a thread to execute forever,
then you simply need to put it in
a loop that runs indefinitely.
So you would say, while true, or
you'd say four and just have a four with
no condition expression that
ever causes it to terminate.
Obviously, you need to be careful
about this in production systems,
because, often times,
you need to shut threads down.
And we'll talk more about that later.
After run returns the thread is no
longer considered to be alive, so if you
called the is alive method, it would
return false after it's been shut down.
You can use another method called Join,
which is important and
is used in various programming
assignments that we'll have here,
that allows one thread to wait for
the completion of another.
So, join allows one thread.
It doesn't have to be the thread
that created the thread, by the way.
It could be a different thread.
It allows it to wait for
the thread to complete.
And when the thread completes,
when the thread exits,
then the other thread
can return from join.
And we'll see later that there's
various methods for join.
It's an overloaded method, so it has
time outs, or non time out versions.
Join is what forms something called
a simple means of barrier synchronization.
We'll talk a lot more about
barrier synchronization later.
Barrier synchronization is used
to allow threads to wait for
each other in various ways.
And there are other mechanisms
besides join in Java.
Things like Countdown Latches, and
Cyclic Barriers, and Phasers, and so on.
And I'll give you some pointers
to more information to find about
those things later.
The thread can also simply evaporate,
where nobody waits to join with it.
In which case, it just goes away, and
then the virtual machine and the operating
system recycles the resources that
are associated with the thread.
There's a number of common Java Thread
methods that are worth knowing about.
There are lots of methods, but we are just
going to talk about some of them.
These are the most common ones.
There's one called setDaemon
that marks a thread as a daemon.
A daemon thread is a thread that's
defined in such a way that it's lifetime
is a function of the number of other
nonDaemon threads in the process.
So when all the other nonDaemon
threads exit then any
daemon threads will also exit.
Conversely, with normal threads,
if the main thread exits,
then the other threads
can continue to execute.
There's a method called Start,
as we saw that initiates thread execution.
There's an abstract method called Run
which is a hook method for user code.
That's the method you fill in or
you provide a runnable that fills it in.
There's a method called Join which is used
for various synchronization to wait for
threads to finish.
Sleep is used to wait for a certain
amount of time to elapse, there's
a couple different variants of sleep that
wait for, milliseconds or nanoseconds.
You can find out what the current thread
is by calling currentThread, which is
the Static method that will return
the current thread, which can be used for
debugging purposes and other mechanisms
and other algorithms we'll see later.
There's a couple of interesting ways
of causing threads to shut down.
We're going to have a whole
section about this in a minute.
But in a nutshell, interrupt can be used
to post an interrupt request to a thread.
And that's really the only graceful way
of having threads tell
each other to shut down.
You can't really stop them.
And we'll talk about why
you can't stop them later.
But you can interrupt them.
And that posts a request to a thread.
And then, a thread can test to see
whether or not it's been interrupted, and
there's a couple of ways to do that.
There's a method called isInterrupted,
which is a non static method that checks
to see whether a thread
has been interrupted.
And you can call this method
multiple times without
affecting the status of the interrupt,
and there's another method called
the Interrupted which is a static method.
And this checks to see whether the current
thread has been interrupted or not.
And this actually clears the interrupt
status the first time it's called.
So we'll talk more about
these things later,
they're very important to understand
the differences and how they work.
There are also methods
called setPriority and
getPriority which are used to set and
get the priorities of the threads.
And that's often useful to give a bump or
either a bump up or
a bump down if you want to emphasize
some computations over others.
These methods establish various,
so-called, Happens-Before orderings.
Take a look here, you can find
out more about Happens-Before.
Happens-Before is a very important
concept in Java concurrency, and
in concurrency in general.
Is it deals with how information
is shared and becomes visible and
is made consistent between multiple
threads, which is especially important in
today's multicore platforms, which, pretty
much everything is multicore these days.
For example, when you start a thread,
starting a thread happens before
the run method of the thread is called.
Likewise, when a thread terminates,
the termination of
the thread happens before the join
occurs with the terminated thread.
And there's also many other examples
in Java.util.concurrent of methods that
establish Happen-Before orderings.
So, for example placing an object into
a concurrent collection happens-before
the access or removal of
the element from that collection.
And these are a very important concepts
because if you don't use synchronization
properly you'll have problems with
Happens-Before relationships and
you'll have problems with your
code not being consistent and
visible and ordered properly.
Now, luckily Android takes care
of an awful lot of these problems
in its concurrency frameworks
that we'll talk about later.
So now let's go ahead and
take a look at an example of Starting and
Joining with Java Threads.
And this is an example that you can
actually download here, from this website.
And this demonstrates the use
of various Thread methods
to implement an embarrassingly
parallel application.
So I'll first go ahead and
explain what it does and
then I'll show you
a little bit of the code.
So this particular example spawns a bunch
of threads, these are worker threads and
each of these threads searches for
words in a List of Strings.
We have a List of Strings, and we have
a bunch of Threads and they search for
words in those Threads.
So we're going to call Thread.start()
to spawn a worker Thread for
each element in the List of Strings.
Let's say that there's ten elements in
the List of Strings, we might have ten
Threads, one Thread would search
each String for words in the String.
And then the main thread, and
this is the key point of this example,
is going to use Thread.join to wait for
the worker Threads to finish running.
And that's an example of a simple
form of barrier synchronization.
No other java synchronization
mechanisms are needed for
something that is this simple,
because this is a very straight forward
example that is embarrassingly parallel.
What that means is that
there's really little or
no dependencies between the various
computations that are taking place.
Later we'll talk about other,
more interesting Java synchronization
mechanisms, like synchronized
statements and wait and
notify mechanisms on
Java built in monitor op.
Here's the source code for
the thread join test.
As you can see, this is all in one file.
So let's just kind of walk through the
file, and I will show you how it works.
So Thread join test, you can see it's
got a string, bigger, there we go, so
we've got ourselves an array of strings,
and they have funny names in them.
You'll see why they have these
funny names in a second.
And then there's a list of words
we're going to search for,
which are just the names for
musical notes.
So, what we're going to do is we're
going to spawn a separate thread
the search each of these strings for
the musical notes.
Now, of course, in real life, we probably
wouldn't use an array of strings,
we'd have an array of files, or something
like that, but I'm just trying to keep it
simple to focus on the concurrency and
synchronization aspects.
So we call the class that does this search
one shot thread join, it's going to have
a list of strings as input, and it is
going to have an array of words defined.
And it's also going to have a list of
threads which are the threads that were
created to do the searching, and
then we're also of course going to
use these threads to join with
the results when we're done.
So we come down here and
we have SearchOneShotThreadJoin,
as you can see, well we set
the parameters passed in to the fields.
We make ourselves a linklist of worker
threads, and then we go through
the input size, that's the input we were
given, the list of strings to search.
And for each string in the input,
we go ahead and make a new
task using a factory method called
makeTask that we'll look at in a second.
And we take the task, which is a Runnable,
we make a new thread,
we add that thread to the list of threads
we're going to join with later, and
then we go ahead and start the thread.
So the thread is now running.
So we're going to basically
spawn off a thread for
every element in the input list.
Then down here in the main thread,
we simply iterate through the list of
worker threads, and
we call join on each one.
And join of course will wait
until the thread is finished and
then join will return.
So this loop only exits after all the
threads are done with their processing.
So that's what's called
Barrier Synchronization.
You're using this to wait in
what's called an Exit Barrier.
Here's the factor method that makes
the runable, when we call make task,
we give at the index that we
are going to have in the list.
We make a new runnable,
whose run method we'll go ahead and
look up in the input list,
get the item at that location.
And then it goes ahead and
it calls a method called Process Input.
Keep in mind that this method will be
running in its own thread of control.
And process input simply iterates through
the words that we're looking for.
And it searches in the input
data one word at a time.
And it keeps looking until
it finds all the words.
And every time it finds a match, then it
goes ahead and it processes the result.
And as you'll see in a second,
that just goes ahead and
prints the result to the output.
So it'll indicate whether it found a
particular word in a particular string for
a particular thread.
Then here is just the way
we print things out.
Here's the main program, we go ahead and
start the thread join test.
We go ahead and
we'll create a new instance and knowledge
instance of search one shot thread join,
which will pass in the parameters and
then that'll go ahead and run and
that will wait until it's finished.
And we'll print all the results
out that happen to match.
That's basically that simple program.
You're welcome to take a look at this and
other programs as you see fit.
And you can also go and take a look at the
website for more information about that.