The next topic here is
built-in monitor objects, and
there are two parts to this discussion.
We're going to talk about
what monitor objects are, and
how they can be used to
ensure mutual exclusion and
coordination between threads
running in a concurrent program.
In order to do this, we're going to
show an example of a buggy concurrent
Java program that's going to be
concurrently calling put and
take methods on something
called the SimpleQueue.
And we'll see there that
if we're not careful,
we'll end up corrupting
the internal state.
And we're going to show how to fix this
problem by applying monitor objects.
And as we'll see,
monitor objects will give us a bunch of
different features to make things better.
They give us something called synchronized
methods and statements which use
an entrance queue to ensure only one thing
at a time is running inside the object.
And I'll also use a wait
wueue to be able to wait and
notify to coordinate the interactions
between different threats.
All these features I just described
are something called a monitor.
A monitor is a pattern.
It's a concurrency control construct
that's been around for 40 or 50 years.
It's been around a very long time.
And it's used for
synchronization in concurrent programs.
There are three capabilities a monitor
provides to concurrent programs.
The first thing it provides is it allows
you to ensure only one thread at a time
is able to access critical
sections within an object.
So that's one of the key features.
Mutual exclusion is the fancy way
of saying one thing at a time, and
we'll see some examples of that later.
You can read more about
critical section here.
It also ensures that threads
running in a monitor
can block efficiently waiting for
certain conditions to become true.
So, if you're unable to make forward
progress while you are the one and
only thread running inside a monitor,
then you can step outside the monitor
using what's called a condition.
And you can wait for
the condition expression you're
waiting on to become true.
And then the third thing you can do
is you can notify other threads that
conditions they're waiting
on may have been met.
So that's a way to wake up
people who are waiting.
So those are the three main
things a monitor does, and
we'll talk more about this later.
There's a bunch of human
known uses of monitors.
One example that might be worthwhile to
think about is to make it more intuitive
would be some kind of a hospital room.
Like an operating room in a hospital where
you want to be able to allow people to
queue up waiting to get
access to the operating room,
which is a critical section.
Let's say for hygienic purposes to
reduce the likelihood of infection,
only one person, only one patient can
be in the operating room at a time.
Of course, you can have multiple doctors,
but only one person could be in there.
And they have to wait in a pre-operating
room outside of the critical section for
their turn to come in.
And after they're done, they can go to
a post-operating room to wait to leave.
But only one patient is in
the operating room at a time.
So, let's take a look at a simple example
to motivate why we need to have monitor
objects.
And we'll look at this in a couple
of different vantage points.
The example here is based on
Java's ArrayBlockingQueue.
And so, we'll take a look and
see how an ArrayBlockingQueue works.
Here's a UML sequence diagram that
shows the design of our buggy solution,
and you can find the buggy solution.
If you like to run buggy code and
try to figure out why it's buggy,
you can take a look at the code here for
the buggy solution.
So, we have a main program.
And that main program spawns two threads,
a producer thread and a consumer thread.
Both of which access a simpleQueue.
And then, when those threads start to run,
they alternate or they don't alternate.
They both call put and
take on the simpleQueue concurrently.
And, of course, we'll see in a second
that that causes all kinds of problems
with respect to race conditions.
Which are situations where you're
corrupting the internal state of an object
by having multiple threads
simultaneously try to read and
write its fields in unprotected way.
Here's an example of
a simple BlockingQueue.
It implements the BlockingQueue interface.
And take a look here for
more information about BlockingQueue.
It creates a resizable array
implementation called an ArrayList.
You could read more about ArrayList here.
And then, it has a pair of
non-synchronized public methods,
put and take.
And the idea is that these
are trying to add and
remove the elements from the queue.
It will add an element at the end and
take the element from the front.
So that's what it's trying to do.
Here's the main program.
It goes ahead and
creates this SimpleQueue.
It creates a pair of threads,
a producer and a consumer.
It starts the producer and
consumer threads, and
then those threads begin to run.
As you can see, what they do when
they run is they sit there, and
one thread will put a string to the queue,
and
the other thread will go ahead and
take the string out of the queue.
So that's what we're trying to do.
We're trying to have the two threads
communicate through a SimpleQueue.
The question, of course,
is what's the output of this program and
why does it behave the way it does?
Well, if you run this program,
you'll see it will do bad things.
It will crash and
give you strange results and so on.
And, the reason why, of course,
it does that, is that,
there's several reasons why.
But one of the reasons why is there's no
protection against the critical section,
which is basically the part
that's the shared state,
which is the list, being accessed
concurrently by multiple threads.
And if you read the documentation for
ArrayList,
you'll see it says that the implementation
of ArrayList is not synchronized.
So, if multiple threads try to access it,
then it must be synchronized externally.
And that, of course,
if what we're going to end up doing here
because we're going to be ensuring that
we synchronize these things properly.
So, the problem here has a funny name.
It's a name called a race condition.
And race conditions occur when you
have multiple threads accessing fields
that are not protected by the proper
synchronization mechanisms.
And this is a very tedious and
error-prone thing to try to address.
And, it's why understanding patterns of
effective concurrent programming in Java
is so important, especially if you're
writing Android code, where you
almost have to have concurrent programs,
for reasons we'll talk about later.
We're going to fix all these problems by
applying various built-in monitor object
mechanisms in Java.
And so,
let's start talking about those next.
So, we're going to talk about how to
fix these problems using the several
mechanisms that Java provides.
Java provides a couple of different
built-in monitor object mechanisms.
So, let's talk about them.
All objects in Java can be
used as monitor objects.
And they support two types
of thread synchronization.
They support mutual exclusion,
which allows concurrent access and
updates to shared data fields or
data shared by threads without
incurring race conditions.
So, they solve the issue of concurrency.
And then,
there's also something else that they do.
Oh, and they do this,
they support mutual exclusion
via something that's called
synchronized methods or blocks.
And, basically,
the synchronized methods and
blocks use something
called the Entrance Queue.
And, this is managed internally
by the Java virtual machine, and
we'll talk a bit later on how that
actually works under the hood.
Every Java object has a single so-called
intrinsic lock that's associated with it.
And if you make a synchronized method or
a synchronized statement,
it's that intrinsic lock that's
being acquired and released.
And there's also something
called coordination.
So, every monitor object
also supports coordination.
And that enables threads to cooperatively
schedule their interactions, and
it does this using something
called a wait queue.
And the JVM supports coordination
via a wait queue and
various notification mechanisms
that are built into it.
And we'll talk later about how that works,
as well.
Every job object has a single intrinsic
condition associated with it.
So, there's a single intrinsic lock and
there's a single intrinsic condition.
And that actually causes some issues for
which
other Java synchronization mechanisms
are required, which we'll touch on later.
These mechanisms implement a variant
of the monitor object pattern.
We'll talk a lot about
patterns in this course.
Take a look here, you can read more
about the monitor object pattern.
You can also find out about this from
the Pattern Oriented Software
Architecture Volume Two Book posted, too.
The intent of this pattern is to ensure
that only one method runs within an object
and to allow an object's methods to
cooperatively schedule their execution
sequences.
So, you can see the monitor
Object Pattern is obviously what
Java's Monitor Objects are implementing.
You can also implement monitor object
pattern in other languages besides Java,
like C++, or C-sharp, or
C, or Ada, or whatever.
We're going to use monitor objects to
implement a better solution to the buggy
SimpleQueue and the inefficient
BusySynchronizedQueue solutions.
So, we'll see how that's
all going to work.
Let's first start by talking about
built-in synchronized methods.
These are the most fundamental
part of Java monitor objects.
They're very simple,
somewhat limited, but very simple.
To show these things,
we're going to have something
called the BusySynchronizedQueue.
So this is a way to fix some of
the problems with the SimpleQueue
that we had before.
You can see the BusySsynchronizedQueue
here at this link.
This thing is going to be able
to implement BlockingQueue,
which has a certain set of interfaces we
expect, certain set of methods we expect.
And it's going to have
some internal state,
which is going to be the list and
the capacity.
And those, we want to protect against race
conditions by using synchronized methods.
Here's the constructor.
It initializes the internal state.
Here are the methods,
put, take, and isEmpty.
All of these are marked as synchronized,
and that means only one of
them can run at a time.
And I'll show you how that works.
Only one can run at
a time on a given object.
So that means they're serialized with
respect to other synchronized methods
on an object.
And this is very important.
If you have two different objects, each
of which has synchronized methods, and
they're not static methods,
then calls on those two different
objects can actually run in parallel.
So it's only within
an object that matters.
And you can think about synchronized
is basically a way to provide
so-called fully-bracketed
access to a critical region.
And fully-bracketed means
the thread that acquires the lock,
the intrinsic lock,
to enter the critical section
must be the thread that releases
the lock on the way out.
That's what fully-bracketed means,
and we'll talk about how that works.
When we use these in the method signature,
the access to the entire body
of the method is serialized.
So if we say synchronized here,
this covers everything from open
curly brace to closed curly brace.
We'll see later in a second that there
are other more fine-grained ways to
handle this.
The fine-grained ways, of course,
are called synchronized statements.
As you can see in this example,
we're going to to look at here,
which is actually from Java,
Java has something called the Exchanger.
Synchronized methods can yield
excessive serialization overhead.
So, here's an Exchanger, you can
find out more about Exchanger here.
And what we have is
a method called createSlot,
which is a synchronized method,
as you can see up here, it's synchronized.
And inside of this,
the whole method is synchronized.
And what's going to happen is we're
going to make ourselves a new slot.
And then, we're going to check to see
if an item is initialized or not.
And if it is not initialized,
we're going to initialize it.
So, we're going to lazily create the slot,
if it's the first time that it's accessed,
and this whole method is synchronized.
Which means that,
that entire chunk of code can only have
one thread operate on it at a time.
That turns out to be excessive,
that's more lock-in than we really need,
in this case.
So here is another example
of rewriting this method.
And instead of having synchronized be
part of the signature, instead, we move
synchronized into just the portion of
the method that really needs to be locked.
And this is what's called a synchronized
statement or a synchronized block.
You can read more about
it here at this link.
Synchronized statements are important
because they enable more fine-grained
serialization than synchronized methods,
because we
only need to synchronize a particular
region in a method, not the whole method.
So, for example in this case, these
calls here, where we make a new slot and
we assign an arena to
the local variable a here,
these are actually not synchronized.
I should probably put the word
final before them as well, but
I don't think the Java code
had that when I looked at it.
So, basically,
we're creating a slot outside of the lock
to narrow the region in which
synchronization has to be performed.
And that will help us
get higher concurrency,
especially on a multi-core processor.
So, only this statement here,
within the curly braces,
is serialized by the intrinsic lock.
So this is using the intrinsic lock.
We can also use other kinds of things.
We can explicitly synchronize
with another object.
Every Java object,
it's not a built-in type.
Built-in types would be things like
double, int, float, and so on.
Every Java object can
be used to synchronize,
because every Java object has
an intrinsic lock that's part of it.
We would normally say
synchronize this here, but
we could also say synchronize on a,
which is this arena object down here.
We also see something called
the double-checked locking optimization
pattern.
I'm not going to go into
too much detail right now.
But if you read this link,
you'll find out more about
double-checked locking optimization.
And that's basically what this
code is implementing here.
Okay, so you can read more about
synchronized statements here at this link.
I highly recommend you do it.
You'll have to understand how these things
work in order to do the programming
assignments in the course.
So, you might as well take some
time to read more about it and
ask questions on the discussion forum.
So armed with what we know now,
let's now take a look at a partial
solution using Java synchronized methods.
So this is going to be a partial solution,
so
it's not going to solve all the problems.
Here's our BusySynchronizedQueue example.
As you can see here, we have
synchronized keyword put on take and
put, which means that those
things are serialized.
Only one synchronized method could be
active at a time in a given object.
And adding the synchronized
keyword either in the method or
in a synchronized
statement has two effects.
The first effect is that
invocations of put and
take on the same object can't interleave.
What that means is that
they run atomically.
Put runs to completion before take runs,
or
take runs to completion before put runs.
But we don't have to worry about
them running a little bit of put and
a little bit of take at the same time.
That's one thing that happens.
So this means that each method is atomic.
So if one call to put is
running then a call to take, or
another call to put by different
threads will have to block.
So, that's a way to think about it.
And a second thing that happens is
there's a happens before relationship
that ensures when we add something over
here, when one thread adds something
to the list over here, Tthat that will
be properly propagated over here.
So there will not be inconsistent or
misordered access to memory.
Because, synchronized statements will
flush out the caches as things change.
There are some limitations of
Java synchronized methods, and
that's important to understand what
we're about to talk about next.
So, if we only use them and
we don't do anything else,
we just use synchronize methods or
blocks, then calls to these put and
take methods will busy wait, and
that can lead to all kinds of problems.
The most obvious problem with busy
waiting is that you'll waste CPU cycles,
spinning, doing nothing useful,
like a hamster or
a gerbil in a little running wheel.
So, that's a bad use of things.
There are also potentially problems
with starvation here as well.
But basically spinning is a bad idea for
stuff like this, unless you're
building a hard real-time system to
do something like control
the temperature in a nuclear reactor, or
modify the flight services on an airplane
control wing, or something like that.
So what we need to do,
instead of just busy waiting,
is we need to have some vehicle, some
mechanism, to coordinate put and take so
they don't busy wait when
there is nothing to do.
And, of course, the way to do that,
which we'll talk about in a minute,
is to use the wait and
notify mechanisms provided by Java monitor
objects to provide a convenient and
efficient solution.